A Guide to the Papers of Henry Clay, 1798-1934, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence and Documents
  - John Tyler, Washington, to Henry Clay 1841 April 30, ALS, 4 pp.; docketed; silked. #2362. (Box-folder 2:43)
    Tyler apologizes for not answering Clay's letter earlier. Tyler says that no one should expect him to bring before Congress "matured plans of public policy connected with deeply interesting and intricate subjects." Some issues, such as the "repeal of the subtreasury" and "the state of our military defences" require immediate attention. "It will however be for Congress to decide whether other measures shall claim its attention." Tyler says that his opinions "on the subject of a distribution of the proceeds of the sales of the public lands" were made known three years previous in a report to the Virginia House of Delegates. He says that the "annual appropriation to harbours and rivers" is "wholly indefensible in any view in which I can regard it." In regards to "a Bank...I would not have it urgd [sic] prematurely-The public mind is still in a state of great disquietude in regard to it." He tells Clay that "Jackson tore the charter of the old Bank into tatters-and his followers will go forth as agitators and the result of thier [sic] agitations may prove dissastrous [sic]." Tyler urges Clay to attempt "to frame a Bank as to avoid all constitutional objections" and repeats that he has "no intention to submit any thing to Congress on this subject to be acted on." Tyler closes by saying his "attention is turned to the removals from office after the manner that you suggest."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to the Rev. H.[enry] R. Bascom 1841 May 10, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington May 10. #6004. (Box-folder 2:44)
    Clay says that he will "take pleasure in mentioning to some of the faculty and trustees of Transylvania Dr. [John James] Reese favorably." Clay thanks Bascom for notifying him of "the complaints which have reached you against me of neglect in my correspondence. Clay says that if a day "had 48 instead of 24 hours" it would still be too short to answer the hundreds of letters he received in Washington. He generally did not reply to letters seeking office but hopes that he did not treat any personal letters "with disrespect." Clay closes by telling Bascom of the letter he received from John Tyler; Clay hopes for Tyler's cooperation and support.
  - Henry Clay, S.[enate] Chamber, to O.T. Keeler 1841 July 19, ALS, 1 p. #2375. (Box-folder 2:45)
    Clay received Keeler's letter containing "a Memorial in behalf of the passage of a general bankrupt law" and has presented it to the Senate.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to John R. Thompson 1841 August 14, ANS, 1 p. #5718-c. (Box-folder 2:46)
    Clay writes to Thompson, a University of Virginia student: "In answer to your enquiry about the word 'locate,' I have to say that whether it be an English word or not, I think it a very good American one."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Charles Parrow 1841 August 15, ALS, 1 p. #7661. (Box-folder 2:46a)
    Clay writes concerning legislation in the current session of the United States Congress and predicts failure for the bill to establish the Bank of the United States "which is in the hands of the President, and which is believed he will veto."
  - Henry Clay to Col. [James Watson] Webb [1842, ca. January 26], ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #5694. (Box-folder 2:47)
    Clay writes, possibly in reply to Webb's letter of January 21, 1842, and thanks him for his suggestions. Clay says it "has not been found practicable to delay acting on the repeal of the Bankrupt law." If the repeal is defeated, it will most likely be because of a tie vote.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Col. [James Watson] Webb 1842 January 30, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #5694. (Box-folder 2:48)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of page. Clay asks Webb or Charles King "to render me an act of justice." Henry Wise has dragged Clay's name "in the unfortunate affair of poor [Jonathan] Cilley" and has "totally misrepresented any agency of mine in it." Clay says that on the day of the duel, Charles King consulted him "as to the practicability of arresting it." Clay says that he suggested notifying the police and recommended that King go to Charles F. Mercer and Francis Scott Key for that purpose. Unfortunately, the police "mistook the road, on which the parties left the City." This is the fact that Clay wishes "to be brought out by one or both of you; and in such suitable manner as may be deemed most proper."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Col. J[ames]. W[atson]. Webb 1842 February 12, ALS, 3 pp. docketed. #5694. (Box-folder 2:49)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of p. 1. Clay has received Webb's letter and forwarded the enclosures to the editor of the Washington Daily National Intelligencer. Clay distributed Webb's prospectuses for the New York Courier to a member of the House of Representatives who will canvas for names. Clay says that he has "not made up my mind to consent to the use of my name" as a candidate for the Presidency. The only reason that would make him consent would be "a clear manifestation that my services were desired by a majority of my Country men." Clay says there is not a single Senator "in the Whig ranks, who is not well disposed towards the Whig party, and who is not exempt from all tincture of Tylerism."
  - Papers regarding Henry Clay's connection with the Jonathan Cilley-William J. Graves duel of 1838. 1842, 6 items. #2540. (Box-folder 2:50)
    Statement of Charles King, New York, 1842 Feb. 4 (ADS, 4 pp.)
    Statement of Reverdy Johnson, Baltimore, 1842 Feb. 7 (ADS, 4 pp.; with modern transcription in unidentified hand.)
    William Jordan Graves to Henry Clay, 1842 Feb. 16 (ALS, 5 pp.)
    Paper wrapper with note "Original papers published in Natl. Intell. Feb 25, 1842"
    "Henry Clay on dueling," (printed; reproduces text of Samuel Wood to Henry Clay, 1838 Mar. 8 and Henry Clay to Samuel Wood, 1838 Mar. 23, both re the duel.)
    Printed biography of Jonathan Cilley removed from unidentified source
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Jon. A. Tenney 1842 March 28, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #2180. (Box-folder 2:51)
    Clay tells Tenney that although he generally declines requests for autographs, he is making an exception because of the "friendly sentiments towards me, conveyed in you letter."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to [unidentified recipient] 1842 May 26, ALS, 1 p. #1113. (Box-folder 2:52)
    Clay responds to a request to inform the recipient when he left the United States on the mission to conclude the Treaty of Ghent.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to N.[athan] Sargent 1842 May 31, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington, Jun.1. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:53)
    Clay thanks Sargent for the "Copy of my Valedictory so handsomely printed on Satin." He asks about President Tyler and whether the relationship between him and the Whigs is improved. Clay mentions the "affair" between Edward Stanly and Henry A. Wise. He concludes by mentioning that "Mr. Van Buren" left a few days ago and Clay found him "interesting often & some times amusing." Clay mentions the reception in Lexington given to "the little magician" [i.e. Van Buren] and says he doubts "whether he has had one so imposing any where since he left home."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to N.[athan. Sargent 1842 July 31, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Jul. 31. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:54)
    Clay thanks Sargent for his recent letter and mentions John D. Langhorne. Clay says he is "glad the N.E. question is settled, altho' the terms are curious enough." He wonders what President Tyler "will do with the Tariff, and, if he veto it, what Congress will then do." Clay says Kentucky is blessed with abundant crops and he is "making extensive preparations to Water rot hemp."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Thomas W. Duffield, Jr. 1842 September 6, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Sep. 6. #6306. (Box-folder 2:55)
    Clay thanks Duffield for a copy of an address he had delivered to the literary club of Oxford, Pa. Clay suggests that the club members might usefully debate such topics as the presidential veto, free trade vs. tariff protections or the establishment of a Bank of the United States. Clay says that such debates "might be made highly instrumental in propagating truth & dispelling error."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to A. M. January 1842 September 17, ALS, 1 p. #11159. (Box-folder 2:56)
    Clay will travel to Cincinnati by the Maysville route and will write January "next week informing you, if I can, who will accompany me."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Benjamin Watkins Leigh 1843 March 17, ALS, 3 pp.; postmarked Lexington Mar. 18. #1463. (Box-folder 2:57)
    Clay describes his "Southern jaunt," from which he has just returned. If he should be selected as the candidate of the Whigs for the presidency he believes the vote of Kentucky "is no more certain than that of Louisiana." Clay believes that both Mississippi and Alabama will vote Whig, though "a bitter schism exists on the bank question in Alabama, and on repudiation in Mississippi...and in both on the Presidency." Clay tells Leigh that he "heartily concurs" with the address of the Whig convention in Virginia to the people. He states that the "brief notice with which Mr. Tyler is treated in the address was wise." Clay says there is an omission in the address that he regrets; that is, "Executive power & the veto." He closes with regard to Chapman Johnson, Francis T. Brooke, Robert Stanard and Julia Wickam Leigh.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to B[enjamin]. W.[atkins] Leigh 1843 June 20, ALS, 1 p.; with attached partial address leaf. #1463. (Box-folder 2:58)
    Clay states that he wrote Leigh several weeks ago in reply to Leigh's letter asking "into the origin of Mr. Wise's alienation and his present enmity" towards Clay. Since Clay has had no reply he wonders if his letter miscarried. Clay says he is "surprized and gratified" by the Virginia election results and is confident of success in Tennessee and Indiana. Clay closes with a postscript in which he states that he is "informed from N. York that some of the Intriguers of 1839 are again engaged in active machinations."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to N[athan]. Sargent 1843 September 2, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Sep. 3. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:59)
    Clay thanks Sargent for his letter and tells him to ask Mr. [Josiah] Randall to show him Clay's letter that suggests "a plan of organization." Clay is pleased with Sargent's account of prospects in Pennsylvania and says if the "Whigs and Anti Masons can carry the Legislature at the ensuing election, the whole Nation will resound with joy."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to N[athan]. Sargent 1843 September 19, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Sep. 20. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:60)
    Clay thanks Sargent for his letter and says that he has been indisposed with "the Tyler Grippe." He is pleased with Sargent's report of Pennsylvania's prospects. Clay says that "[w]e shall think about a Com[mitt]ee" though he will be away from home from December until May.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Jno.[John] L. Lawrence 1843 October 5, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf; with envelope, postmarked Lexington, Sep. 11. #5828. (Box-folder 2:61)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of p. 1. Clay thanks Lawrence for his letter. He says that he cannot speak in favor of Daniel Webster as candidate for Vice President. Clay says that before Webster "could be properly even considered, he ought to give some public and unequivocal testimony of adherence to the Whig cause." Clay says that "under no circumstances, in my opinion, ought Mr. Webster's name to be used as a Candidate for the V.P." Clay concludes by stating that the "treachery of Mr. Tyler ought to inspire the greatest caution with the Whig party."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Thomas H. Baird 1843 November 1, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached partial blank leaf. #6236. (Box-folder 2:62)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of p. 1. Clay says that if he did not know of Baird's "fidelity and attachment" he would have been "mortified" at Baird's recent letter. Clay is surprised that "any doubt should be entertained of my devotion to the policy of cherishing our manufactures, or that any impression should be made upon a friend by a perversion of my meaning, by an enemy...." Clay then presents a lengthy explanation of his stand on revenue, tariff and the government's debt. He concludes by saying that he would have to "pile letter upon letter until they reached a Mountain height, if I were to write to correct every perversion of my meaning and misrepresentation of me that are made."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to A[aron]. B[alderston]. Quimby 1843 November 8, ALS, 1 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Nov. 9. #2338. (Box-folder 2:63)
    Clay thanks Quimby for his letter and the copy of his letter to Mr. Clayton [not present]. Clay does not think it wise to attack the "two gentlemen mentioned in your letter" since it is not necessary to the success of the Whig cause.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to "Gentlemen" 1843 December 12, ALS, 1 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Dec. 13. #3920. (Box-folder 2:64)
    Clay is honored by the invitation to visit Wilmington, N.C. He hopes he will be able to visit en route to Raleigh, N.C. but "[d]istance of time and place prevents a positive decision at present." A list of twelve names (Alex. Anderson, Edwd. B. Dudley, Thomas F. Davis, Alex. Macrae, W.C. Lord, John Potts Brown, A.J. De Rosset, James F. McKee, P.K. Dickinson, James S. Green, John McKae and Wm. A Wright) in an unidentified hand follows Clay's signature.
  - Legal brief in the case of Joseph Ray [1843], AD, 7 pp. on 2 sheets, in Clay's hand. #2467, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:65)
    Clay's brief for the suit of Joseph Ray, consul at Pernambuco, Brazil, 1816-1817, against the Brazilian government, mentions John C. Calhoun and Henry A. Wise.
  - Henry Clay, Macon, [Ga.], to "Gentlemen" 1844 March 17, ALS, 3 pp.; with attached address leaf. #1649, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:66)
    Clay replies to members of the National Clay Club. He states that it "is to be inferred from your letter" that there are "differences among my Philadelphia friends" and urges them to "unite in a spirit of mutual concession and conciliation, as a band of brothers in the great struggle which is before us."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Henry White 1844 June 15, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Jun.15. #5718-e. (Box-folder 2:67)
    Clay thanks White for his letter and says he is "rejoiced to hear that the merchants of Phila. are animated by such liberal and patriotic zeal. Clay says that regardless of what "we may think of the nominations of our opponents, it is always wisest, in politics as well as War, Never to despise an enemy but to go to work as if Napoleon or Wellington were in the field. If we act in that way, and according to that maxim, we shall drive our opponent out of the Union to find refuge in Texas." Clay closes by saying he will be happy to serve White "with the Planter of Louisiana."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin]. W[atkins]. Leigh 1844 July 3, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #1403. (Box-folder 2:68)
    "Private" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay encloses copies [not present] of his "famous letters to Mr. [Francis P.] Blair" and says that he does not object to Leigh's "shewing them to any person you please." Clay does not want them published without his consent. He says that he is "a little ashamed of ever having been on terms of such intimacy with so great a scoundrel as I now believe Blair to be." Clay closes by saying he is "now considering whether I shall not attack the Jackson party."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Dr. Conway D. Whittle 1844 July 8, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #7973. (Box-folder 2:69)
    Clay says "military land in Missouri is liable to forfeiture for the non payment of taxes." Clay suggests that White's "immediate attention to the subject is advisable if you have any military lands in Missouri."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to B[enjamin]. W[atkins]. Leigh 1844 July 20, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #1403. (Box-folder 2:70)
    Clay is "vexed with applications, chiefly from Virginia" to allow the publication of his Francis P. Blair letters. Clay has no objection "to any gentleman of either party reading the letters" but has not yet decided to publish the letters. He has two objections, "one of which is the violation of the confidence due to private correspondence, and the other is the allusion to an infirmity of Mr. [John Quincy] Adams." Clay has not "received all the proof I expect to establish 'bargain intrigue & corruption,' upon [Andrew] Jackson and his friends. He closes with comments on the political situation in Tennessee, Virginia, South Carolina and Kentucky.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Geo[rge]. M. Davis 1844 August 31, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Sep. 2. #2802, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:71)
    "Private" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay is somewhat disappointed in the election results in Illinois. He declines to make a public statement "on the subjects of the Naturalization Laws and the Native American party." He sends Davis an issue of the Lexington Reporter [not present] "which comprehends abundant matter defending me against the charge of liberality to foreigners."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Henry White 1844 September 19, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Sep. 20. #1649. (Box-folder 2:72)
    Clay thanks White for his letter and hopes that the success of the "Commercial Committee" will "correspond with its good intentions." Clay says "our intelligence concerning" the 1844 gubernatorial election in Pennsylvania "is somewhat conflicting." He mentions the Whig committee in Washington organized by Garrett Davis and Willis Green. Clay closes by saying he will be happy to serve White's "house with the sugar planters in Louisiana" if he is able.
  - A. Webster, Secretary of the Clay Club of Plainfield, to the President of the Clay and Frelinghuysen Club of New Brunswick 1844 September 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed; postmarked Sep. 24 Plainfield N.J; on blue paper illustrated with portraits of Clay and Frelinghuysen, with the caption "Huzza! Huzza! the Country's risin.'" #3417-b. (Box-folder 2:73)
    Webster writes concerning the organization of a mammoth mass meeting to be held on September 26 in support of Clay's candidacy.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Benjamin Watkins Leigh 1844 September 30, LS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; docketed; Barrow. #1403. (Box-folder 2:74)
    Clay has been "much urged by Mr. [John] Pleasants and other friends in Virginia, to allow the publication of my [Francis P.] Blair letters." Clay says his "opinion from the first has been, that their publication, so far from injury would benefit me in respect to the charge of bargain." If Leigh and others in Virginia think publication will help, Clay has no objections. He asks that if the letters are published "it would perhaps be best to say, that it was done by friends of Mr. Clay upon their own responsibility...Credit should be claimed for me, which I think I deserve for abstaining from the publication on account of the private playful and familiar character of the letters, although the evidence which they contain in regard to the public charge, is really beneficial to me." Clay discusses the public accessibility of the letters over the years and states that the contents do not differ substantially from his letter to his constituents in March 1824. Clay closes by stating that this letter "has been written by an amanuensis upon my dictation, although I am happy to tell you, that my health is now excellent and never was better."
  - Campaign ribbon for the Clay-Frelinghuysen campaign [ca. 1844], ca. 23 x 7 cm. #3417-b. (Box-folder 2:75)
    Silk[?] ribbon, with portrait of Clay and text: Henry Clay / The people's choice / The pride of America / Freylinghuysen
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Joseph Story 1845 February 9, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:76)
    Clay states that he is not surprised that Story is considering stepping down from the Supreme Court. Clay says that Story's "friends would rejoice if you could reconcile it to your feelings to continue; but most certainly, after what you have said to me, the question should be left to your exclusive judgment."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland to Peter Cromwell, Fishkill Landing, N.Y. 1845 February 17, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Feb. 16. #3121. (Box-folder 2:77)
    "Private" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay thanks Cromwell for his letter and the "friendly sentiments" it contained about the "late Presidential election." Clay says he entertains "many serious apprehensions" about the future and hopes that the American people "will perceive impending dangers and guard against them."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Mr. [Henry L.] Ellsworth 1845 March 24, ALS, 1 p. #3417-b. (Box-folder 2:78)
    Clay encloses a letter [not present] from "two of the most enterprising and reputable citizens of Louisville" concerning an experiment to produce "an efficient Hempbrake."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland to John L. Lawrence, New York 1845 April 30, LS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with cover. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:79)
    "Private" above salutation. Clay thanks Lawrence for his recent letter and mentions that he has received a Baltimore newspaper "containing what occurred in the British House of Commons on the Oregon subject." Clay has long believed that difficulties "would arise out of the headlong course of our Government in respect to Oregon, at the very moment when a negotiation is in progress with Great Britain." Clay believes it "premature" to settle the Pacific coast and maintain defences "at a time when we have quite enough to defend the coasts of the Atlantic Ocean and the Gulph of Mexico." Clay says that he is apprehensive "that we are shortly to have war with both England and Mexico. The party in power has not the moral courage to do right." Clay fears that Great Britain will, because of the annexation of Texas, see "dangers to all her American possessions ahead" and possibly craft an alliance with Mexico. Such an alliance would be "capable of inflicting much mischief, especially on the Pacific." Clay believes "that there is a strong possibility of war." He asks Lawrence to send him a full report of Lord Russell's speech if possible. Clay closes with a postscript stating, "I have dictated the above to an amanuensis."
  - Henry Clay and James B. Clay to Thomas Grubbs 1845 August 1, ADS, 1 p. #4925. (Box-folder 2:80)
    Promissory note for $350 at 6% interest.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to [Henry] C. [Westervelt] 1845 September 20, ALS, 1 p.; with address cut from leaf or cover; docketed; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Sep. 21. #3193. (Box-folder 2:81)